Now here we will talk about how in some projects a scope creep may happen,
سنتحدث الآن عن بعض التغييرات الخاصة بتوسُّع نطاق العمل،
that could be detrimental to
وهذا الأمر قد يضر
the freelancers relationship with the client and the project.
بعلاقة الموظف الحر مع العميل والمشروع.
But first let's try to understand what a scope creep is.
ولكن دعونا أولًا نحاول فهم المقصود بتوسُّع نطاق العمل.
In the last lesson,
في الدرس الأخير،
we talked in detail about a project score that you and the client would agree upon.
تحدثنا بالتفصيل عن نتائج ومخرجات المشروع التي ستتفق عليها أنت والعميل.
This is a detailed document explaining
هنا نجد ملف مفصل يشرح
the features of work streams that you will work on in the project.
سمات المسارات التي ستعمل عليها في المشروع.
Now let's say you and the client agreed on requirements A,
لنفترض أنك اتفقت مع العميل على المتطلبات أ،
B, C, and D for a project.
ب، ج، د لمشروع ما.
After a while,
بعد فترة،
client also adds requirement A1,
وجدت أن العميل أضاف المتطلب أ1،
which as per the client's claim was anyway a part of A1,
ووفقًا للعميل فهو يعتبر هذا الطلب الإضافي جزء من أ1،
whereas per you it was not a part of the original score and is a new requirement.
بينما تجد أنت هذا الطلب لا يُعد جزءًا من المخرجات الأساسية. وبذلك تعتبره متطلب جديد.
This is a scenario in which a scope creep has happened.
وهذا هو السيناريو الذي يحدث فيه توسُّع نطاق العمل.
While you as a freelancer have the opinion that
فأنت ترى كموظف حر أن هذا
a new requirement is added in the middle of the project which was not decided earlier.
متطلب جديد تمت إضافته في منتصف المشروع ولم يتم إقراره في البداية.
Scope creeps could create misunderstandings and
قد يخلق توسُّع نطاق العمل سوء تفاهم
frustrations amongst both the client and the freelancer.
وإحباط لدى كلًا من العميل والموظف الحر.
Sometimes they even become the cause of the client and the freelancer parting ways.
وقد يتسبب أحيانًا في إنهاء العلاقة بين العميل والموظف الحر.
But the question is, what to do when a scope creep happens?
والسؤال هنا ماذا يجب أن تفعل عند حدوث توسُّع نطاق العمل؟
Now, really the best strategy to deal with a scope creep is to avoid it.
والآن، فإن الاستراتيجية الأفضل حقاً للتعامل مع توسُّع نطاق العمل تتلخص في تجنبه.
You can avoid it by having
ويمكنك تجنب الأمر من خلال الحصول على
a detailed enough requirements specification at the start of the project.
مواصفات مفصلة واضحة للمتطلبات في بداية المشروع.
This will significantly help reduce the chances of a scope creep,
سيساعد ذلك بشكل كبير على تقليل فرص حدوث توسُّع نطاق العمل،
and will also help the client think clearly about the project.
كما سيساعد العميل على التفكير بوضوح في المشروع.
Now the second important thing to keep in mind is that scope creeps do happen.
الآن، من المهم أن نضع في اعتبارنا أن توسُّع نطاق العمل أمر وارد الحدوث.
Things do change in the course of the project and when they happen,
فالأمور تتغير أثناء العمل في المشروع، وعندما يحدث هذا،
it is important to educate the client and while
من المهم أن تخبر العميل
you as a freelancer think that a requirement is out of scope.
أنك كموظف حر تعتقد أن المتطلب الجديد خارج نطاق المشروع.
If the client agrees,
إذا وافق العميل على ذلك،
calculate the Delta effort and give a new effort estimate to the client.
احسب الجهد المبذول وأعط العميل تقديرًا جديدًا للجهد.
If the client is convinced that it is a new requirement,
إذا كان العميل مقتنعًا بأنه مطلب جديد،
they may be happy to factor in the new cost or time required to work on the requirement.
فلن يُمانع في حساب التكلفة الجديدة أو الوقت اللازم للعمل على تحقيق هذا المطلب.
That said, sometimes the client is indeed right,
وهذا يؤكد أن العميل أحيانًا يكون على حق،
or sometimes the Delta effort is not so much as to put the whole contract in jeopardy.
وفي بعض الأحيان قد لا يكون الجهد المبذول كبير لدرجة تستدعي تعريض عقد العمل للخطر.
If that's the case,
إذا كان الأمر كذلك،
it is in your best interest to give benefit of doubt to the client
فمن مصلحتك أن تتغاضى عن موقفك،
and go ahead and work on the requirement as part of the original estimate.
وتستمر في العمل على تلبية هذا المطلب كجزء من التقدير الأساسي للمشروع.